This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Hi everyone. I'm Priyanka Ragun for
Software Engineering Radio. Today I'm
chatting with Han Yuan who has more than
two decades of experience in guiding
high-growth, high-scale organizations
for better growth. Having been employed
at
various companies that are small as 25
people to Fortune 500 companies, unicorn
class startups, and organizations in
between. Han has personally initiated
over half a dozen reorganizations
impacting hundreds of individuals and
has been a participant of various
restructuring efforts and hence the
right guest to help us understand the
topic of reorganizations. We will try
breaking down the reason and intentions
behind reorgs and hopefully having
someone like Han tell us what happens
behind the scenes will make us more
enlightened, I hope. So, welcome to the
show, Han. I'm excited to be here. It's
going to be a fun topic. Okay, so let's
jump right in and the first question I
wanted to ask you is how do you define a
reorg and what is the reason why a
company or companies go for a reorg? I
define a reorg as any kind of shuffling
of roles and responsibilities that
impact, you know, at least more than two
groups. I think if you shuffle around
within a team, it sort of doesn't count
like, "Hey Priyanka, I'm going to
promote you to a technical lead." But if
you have two teams and their their roles
are changing, I consider that to be a
reorg. And of course, depending on the
scale of the reorg, things can be more
complex accordingly. In terms of like
the reasons, I thought about this
deeply. I think there are potentially a
lot of reasons, but there are sort of
the five mainstream reasons that I can
come up with. The first one is
operational efficiency. As you become a
bigger and bigger company, eventually
you'll find that the way you're
structured might be slowing you down.
And so, it's sort of like in technology
and software, we have like similar
issues, right? You imagine you wrote a
piece of software, you're hosting it,
but it's just not efficient because of
the way it works. It could be a
monolith. You need to deploy the whole
code at once. It's impacting your CI/CD
pipeline. It's fundamentally
inefficient. And you could potentially
increase, you know, hosting spend or
potentially hire a lot more people to do
the same thing or potentially you could
rewrite it so that the operating costs
and the hosting costs are lower. And you
know, similarly, sometimes companies run
into the same issue where the way we do
work is inefficient. And so, they'll
rethink like, "Hey, how do we reorganize
the assets that we have to be able to do
the same work with less money." You
know, related to that is just
straight-up financial health. For most
software companies, human resources cost
is the number one cost. And so, in order
to dramatically impact, you know,
financial health in a positive way in
cases where spend is too high, that's
where layoffs occur. When you have a
layoff, you're effectively sort of doing
the same thing, right? You're saying,
"Hey, we need to continue doing the same
things but with fewer people." And so
now all of a sudden, you have fewer
people, you have a bunch of empty seats.
What are the roles that need to be
filled? You could have a strategic
shift. You're entering new markets. You
could be, you know, divesting new
markets. In those cases, you might need
people of new skills that were different
than the folks that you had. One of the
more famous stories that, you know, many
folks I'm sure on your program are aware
of is when Netflix moved to the cloud,
they had a bunch of data center folks
and they decided to let them go because
the data center folks had a skill set
that was very, very different than the
cloud engineering operations that
Netflix is well known for today. That
was a major strategic shift that
ultimately helped them move into
streaming in a very, very aggressive
way. You could have M&A. Two companies
join and as a result, there could be
duplication of roles. So again,
reshuffling. And sometimes you just have
external changes. COVID, for example.
When COVID hit, a lot of companies
panicked. They laid off a bunch of
people. Then all of a sudden, business
is awesome and they hired a bunch of
people, right? That's an external
change. I do think things like
technological shifts like generative AI
could have a huge impact. A very
specific example, you got to wonder like
how companies like Stack Overflow
are going to survive in this new world.
You know, they've had a huge hit in
traffic. Other examples include Quora,
right? Where if you go to Quora these
days, they actually show some generative
AI answers. It's interesting because for
those brands to survive, they need to
have a major strategic shift and maybe
the personnel that they had before, it's
not going to fit the new world. Now,
there are a couple of other things that
I think folks sometimes dream up. A new
leader gets hired like a fancy VP and
they're like, "I want to put my stamp on
the organization and I'm just going to
reorg a bunch of people so that looks
good on my performance review." I'm not
going to say that doesn't happen, but
that's not usually a mainstream case.
Another case is you could have somebody
who, you know, wants to bring in past
coworkers and things like that and so
they need to clear room. That does
happen as well. I would consider them
somewhat fringe cases that, you know,
generally do not impact folks beyond
senior leadership.
That's really fantastic. So, what really
piqued my interest from what you just
now said was also, if I Is there another
case where I'm thinking about like I
guess it's similar to the strategic
intent that you said. So, foresight.
Sometimes I don't understand this like
I've I've had uh cases in the past
examples where been part of an
organization where there's, you know,
there's this fantastic research team
which is doing really cutting-edge
research and then suddenly one day that
uh unit is just shut down. The reasoning
is of course they don't really give you
very many reasons to everyone, but do
you have, you know, some take on that?
Like does foresight play also very big
role in this or is that also like would
you say pretty low in the ranking of why
you would do a reorg? What do you mean
by foresight? Like you feel there is
this cutting-edge research that That's
what I'm saying that someone's working
on, maybe like this generative AI, but
then at some point everybody's thinking,
"Oh, this is this cool team that's doing
this really awesome work." And then the
team is just shut down, you know? So, I
just want to know about that kind of
cases. Why does that kind of a thing
happen? Because they seem like these
shining stars that, you know, nothing
can touch and then they're also affected
by it. It's funny you should ask because
that happened to me before. I used to be
the head of engineering for the eBay
equivalent of Google X. So, it was like
a big incubator inside eBay Inc before
eBay and PayPal split. So, I know this
problem really well. I'll tell you why
it happens. I think for businesses,
ultimately, whether or not a group is
effective comes down to three things. Is
your team helping the company make
money? Is your team helping the company
save money? Or is your team helping the
company save time? And I think the
innovation teams that you're describing,
they typically have a very finite window
to be able to generate, you know,
significant results. The problem is that
when economic headwinds come, that
window starts to shrink dramatically.
The only way those groups are typically
protected is they need to be protected
at the board or at the CEO level where
they're willing to run them as loss
leaders. So, when I first joined eBay
the first time, I had a very similar
role. Within the first two to three
months, we took over eBay mobile and it
went from $100 in GMB to $3.3 billion in
GMB in 22 months. For the company,
they're like, "Okay, that's pretty
good." Right? There's innovation works.
The second time I was there, after a
stint where I joined Netflix, we spent
two and a half years there and we did
not have a hit. We tried a bunch of
different things. I think the the
company was very impressed with sort of
the things that we were trying to do and
sort of the PR that we were generating
at the time. The reality is that we were
not helping make money. We were not
helping them save time. We were not
helping them save money. And when push
comes to shove and Carl Icahn comes in
and blows the company up, you know, we
just could not survive. Okay, so that
makes sense. So, actually it almost
looks like the biggest reason for reorg
must be mostly financial. And I guess
the question I wanted to ask you on
this, how do leaders then decide which
group is impacted? What are these
behind-the-scenes discussions like?
There's usually a thesis. So, if it's
not directly financial like we need to
shave X millions of dollars. So, let's
take that case. You know, more around
operational efficiency. Typically, what
happens is an executive needs to
describe a problem statement. These are
the reasons why we need a reorg. For
example, we might want to split the
group up into two divisions and allow
them to operate independently as
full-stack organizations so that they
could operate autonomously. And today,
it's all mixed up. Maybe you have a head
of engineering and a head of product and
they have two silos, right? And so now
you need to mix it. But the intention is
to allow two product lines to run
simultaneously. That is a problem
statement. You design a solution to
solve that, right? Like what would
success look like in that environment?
What are the missing pieces? And then
you start shuffling people around on
paper without people knowing. That's how
that conversation typically starts. The
financial conversation is, I think,
typically started with just a number.
And then when that happens, it goes down
to the next level which is what is the
departmental level spend. And there may
be benchmarks around what the industry
is spending, especially if you're
publicly traded. R&D, for example, there
are If you're publicly traded, R&D spend
is something that folks really look at
very carefully around comparables. So,
if you're say a technology marketplace,
you might be expected to have R&D as a
function of spend to be somewhere around
15%. If you're say an infrastructure
company like Snowflake, you might be
given a lot more leeway in terms of
spend, and so you could have now 30% or
40%. But some of these may be guided by
external investor pressures that you
have to hit that number. From there,
there's a sort of Russian doll aspect to
it to look at, well, now which groups
are more expensive, which groups are
not, and that's where the targeting
comes in. I mentioned this because if
you're a leader and you have a budget,
one of the best ways you can do to
shield your team is to always think
about how efficient are you. It's very
tempting as a leader to think, I want to
grow my career and I want to manage
hundreds of people or, you know, dozens
of people. It might make me look good or
make me feel good. But the opposite
happens when things get rough and you're
in these conversations, you're the one
that's asked to pick and choose who
stays and who goes, and that's not a
very fun place to be. They might have
trouble sleeping at night, I guess.
Let's also talk a little bit about the
operational efficiency angle, and in
that, I guess I should ask you about two
laws. One is, of course, the Conway's
law, and then the other one on theory of
constraints. Now, how does that relate
to reorganization? Is that used a lot
when you actually plan a reorg? It is. A
very specific example, I was at a
company once where the teams were all
mixed up, and they were really kind of
separated to some degree by entities in
the system. So, you can think like users
or checkout or something like that,
right? But then there are like a sort of
business initiatives, and some of the
business initiatives are making what the
features and functions that work right
now work better. And then there are a
bunch of initiatives that are designed
to attract new customers. Now, you can
imagine a world where, like, the folks
that are handling existing customers,
they have a different operating cadence.
They have a different go-to-market
strategy. Maybe their UIs are radically
different. Maybe they even want to use
different frameworks. But the teams were
all mixed together. And so, this case,
you know, how the outside world sees
your products maybe as two different
things, like these are existing
customers and these are new customers,
are very different than the way your
teams are structured. And so, eventually
you have to marry the two. And that's
the idea behind Conway's law, which is
your organization ultimately mirrors how
people consume your products. That
definitely drives things, and over a
period of time you will see shifts. When
you're in a mixed-up state, oftentimes
you're limited in efficiency. You're
constrained, right? There's like kind of
a limiting step. It could be like, oh, I
need to hand off, you know, this piece
of work to this team now, or this team
needs to surface an API to me, and so
therefore, I'm stuck, right? Those are
the kinds of conversations that sort of
you have across the aisle that may slow
things down that otherwise need have to
be if you were all, say, working on the
same team. And so, those constraints,
once you identify, are important because
the idea behind theory of constraints
is, if you think about, say, developing
software as a pipeline of activities, as
software engineers, we get really
excited about making things better,
right? But the truth of the matter is,
there's probably one thing that we're
all doing in our work that's or in our
process or something that is the
limiting step. Like, that is the one
thing that is really clogging up the
system. And so, we could make things
better ahead of the pipeline, or we
could make things better behind the
pipeline, but it won't make the whole
system smoother. And so, a part of
reorganizations is both being very
mindful of whether or not our
organization reflects the products we
build while simultaneously unlocking
those constraints in the system that may
oftentimes be a function of how teams do
the work, specifically in handoffs. So,
you know, taking a cue from this, I
guess the other question I wanted to ask
you is, it sometimes feels that some
organizations are fairly stable, whereas
other organizations uh seem to change
very frequently. Is there any science
behind that? In my personal experience,
it has a lot to do with leadership. One
of the fascinating things about
companies is many companies will have
like core values, but how the company
operates is somewhat a reflection of the
leadership. It starts at the very top.
You'd be very surprised at how much
impact, say, the CEO has on the culture
of the company. Like, their personal
quirks will resonate across the company.
What I will also say, though, is that
just like an organization has a
hierarchy, right? Like a tree, the nodes
underneath the CEO also create a
hierarchy. And so, they create their own
subcultures, so it's like a Russian
doll. And so, stable organizations
sometimes can be, even if the company as
a whole is chaotic, if the executive
owning the group operates in a fairly
stable way, or if they have strong
protections in terms of how they do the
work, they can create stability. One of
the things I think folks don't fully
understand with respect to how
executives work is a big part of
executive work is to be able to
communicate the value of their
organization to everybody else, not just
the CEO, but also the stakeholders and,
you know, all of the middle managers.
When you've done a good job explaining
the relevance of your organization, how
you're utilized, how effectively you're
managing spend, how you're helping the
company make money, save money, or save
time, you have a much better chance of
creating stability for your
organization. And so, for experienced
leaders, this is a top-of-mind issue all
the time. Because there's two kinds of
reorgs, right? There's you, let's say
you're head of engineering, and you're
like, I want engineering to work better,
so now I'm just going to mess with
things. There's a totally different
scenario, which is outside forces
saying, "Hey, you need to change." You
forcing that change via financial or
whatever reason, you have to have the
mechanisms to justify that.
Okay, so then in that case, I think
it'll be a perfect segue to understand a
little bit about the organizational
behavior. So, there are some questions I
wanted to ask you in this regard. So,
why is it that it appears like there are
some people who are in the know of this
reorganization and some are not? So,
what's the kind of pros and cons of,
say, the company or the organization
letting people know that a restructuring
is going to happen? Could you maybe
explain that with maybe an example? I've
done it all ways. My personal preference
is to give people visibility that a
restructuring is going to happen. At the
very high level, give them some
guardrails around when it's going to
happen. I think people can take bad news
if it's expected. I also think that
cases where there's going to be a
serious systemic shock, I think the
right thing to do is to give people the
agency to potentially be able to look
for other work. Because a lot of times
individuals know that they're
underperforming, and to give the
opportunity for the underperformers to
self-select out, I would argue, is
financially beneficial for the company
because you don't need to pay severance
as well. And so, I think in that case,
it's a win-win. The downside is that if
you do not have your ducks in a row and
you do not execute this fast. So, let's
say like, "Hey, we're going to do a
reorg and it'll be finished, you know,
February of next year." What a disaster,
right? Everybody's going to be
paralyzed, they're going to be worried,
nobody's going to be working, it's no
good, right? So, you want to be
organized before you let people know,
and you need to have a process in mind
around how you're going to execute it.
Once you have the transparency, you can
bring people over the curtain and
discuss this. In terms of people who are
typically in the know, I would say they
have two qualities. One is, they have
visibility in the chain of executive
leadership. And that's really important
because if I don't know who you are, I
don't know how to bring you under the
curtain. Or if somebody else doesn't
know who you are, they don't know how to
seek your advice. The other piece that
is critical is somebody who has insight
into the quality of the work of other
people. So, there are certain
individuals that are more accessible in
this regard. You'll find that program
managers oftentimes are brought into the
loop, even junior program managers. And
the reason is because they interact with
a lot of people, and they have
visibility into the contributions of
those individuals. Managers, of course,
are brought into the loop. You'll
strangely find is that sometimes middle
managers, especially managers of
managers, like directors and things like
that, they're not brought into the loop.
The reason is because, A, they could be
impacted by, say, a riff, and then, B,
many times they don't know how the work
is actually done. You know, for better
or worse, they're ineffective, and
they're basically a pass-through. It's
fairly nuanced. You know, a bonus would
be the individual has to have
discretion. There are certain
individuals in the company that are
known to be gossipers, and that will
make things very, very difficult when
you execute a reorg.
So, what are the sort of best practices
that you've seen in your various roles
uh conducting a reorg? What's the best
way to create a discussion about the
reorganization with your leadership
team, coming from a CEO? The most
successful reorgs really nail the why.
They're very good at explaining, why are
we doing this, down to each individual
move that may be controversial. I think
unsuccessful reorgs appear random, they
appear arbitrary, they appear unfair.
But if you play back those reasons, and
maybe you have reasons, too, right?
Reorgs you've experienced. Think if you
do the five why exercise, you'll realize
that actually you don't understand why.
Why was that innovation team let go,
which was one of your earlier questions,
right? We don't know, and then people
have those questions. But if you were
told, like, "Hey, they were costing a
lot of money, it didn't look like
anything was going to be produced in a
while, and it's either their salaries or
or maybe yours," then maybe you'd be
okay with it. Being able to communicate
the why in a respectful but transparent
way, I think, is the key. Too often
leaders want to just move on, to
reshuffle everybody, but they're like,
"Okay, take a break, and let's go
tomorrow." It doesn't really work that
way. You really have to work with the
organization to heal after a significant
change. That's really insightful. So, be
transparent about the reorg, the whys,
as you said, and then the second thing
you said is also give time to actually
soak in the reorg. So, I think yeah,
those are the two main things right
here. There's some work to be done
around identifying those key individuals
that you want to stay and work with
them.
The other thing I wanted to ask also in
in terms of the culture of the company
and how it impacts the uh reorg which
you kind of talked briefly about in the
beginning. Would you have examples like
you know, specific examples that you
don't have to name companies, but where
the culture uh you know, really helped
the reorganization and it went well or
maybe it would also be nice if it's
maybe linked to some countries like if
you're from Bhutan where they have this
happiness index or something. Is the
reorg better in a country like that than
say like a I don't know, any other
country. I'm not naming anything else,
but yeah, that's what I wanted to ask
there. I think the best example is
Netflix. You know, for context for your
listeners, I was at Netflix circa
2010-2011.
I was in charge of the mobile efforts at
the time which was very nascent at the
company. So, I helped lead the teams
that built many of the mobile products
today. And we also played a role in
evolving Chromecast and things like that
with Google direct. So, I was there for
a while. The period of time that I was
there was some of the most hectic times
ever. Carl Icahn tried to break up
Netflix, too. The company tried to split
itself from DVD and streaming. There was
also a big price change at the time, the
first that it was ever done. And so,
there were, you know, massive subscriber
discontent and and cancellations. We
also launched in 32 countries in Latin
America and then UK and Ireland. And
then finally, this is all old news, but
during that time we also went into
original content. That was all happened
in the 15 months that I was there.
Okay, so there's a lot of change, right?
A lot of systemic pressures. I remember
there was an organization that made a
mistake in one of our country launches
and 100 people lost their jobs after one
of the country launches out of nowhere.
What's interesting about Netflix is it
was totally normal. Like nobody was
panicked. People just expected it. And
the reason is because Netflix has this
very complex culture deck which they
they share with everybody and they
really talk about how they don't view
employees as part of a family. They view
them as part of a team. And they're very
clinical in terms of how they make
personnel decisions. And so, when you
join the company, you know this. For
many times during my time there, in the
company was, you know, at times we
didn't have enough office space. And so,
I did not have a cube. So, I sat in the
hallway with a portable desk. But
occasionally, the janitor would move my
desk. I tell you the story because every
time the janitor moved my desk, people
assumed I got fired. And so, when they
would see me walking around the halls,
they're like, I can't believe you're
still here. I'm like, I'm still here.
I'm doing a great job. They wouldn't
fire me. But it's just part of the
culture. And so, if you happen to be in
that culture where change is normalized,
people are okay with it. And that they
did a amazing job of allowing those
people who are okay with, you know,
pretty dramatic change to be able to
just slough that off. Counter example is
is Google. So, I've never worked at
Google, but you know, Google did some
pretty big changes this year. I know a
lot of people who worked at Google. And
when you join Google for like, you know,
the last 10, 15, 20 years, it's
effectively getting tenure at you know,
a university. People expect it to be
lifelong employment. And so, the idea of
layoffs or the idea of your friends
getting laid off is such an anathema
that folks at Google are really
struggling today. And it's because the
way the culture was centered
historically versus the reality of what
they had to do is jarring. And of
course, you know, leadership has
changed, right? Across time. This is no
longer Larry and Sergey's company. But
you know, that cultural shift has to be
managed in a way that is not so jarring.
You could also make the argument you
need to pull the band-aid at some point.
It's going to have a huge impact in
terms of how your organization evolves.
And so, a lot of this homework in terms
of what happens after a reorg is
probably already laid bare in the
foundations of the culture and values of
your company.
That's I think two very good examples. I
think you've driven home the point very.
So, thank you for that. And I think now
we can segue a little bit into say
software and reorg like how you would
say build software and reorgs. Do they
play a part? So, a lot of questions are
coming from that. The first thing is I
wanted to ask is in terms of certain
companies you have like a product
function and an engineering function
which is separate. But sometimes they
get combined into one function like
chief product and technology officer.
So, what are the pros and cons of having
this approach? The biggest pro is that
you have one person who owns both sides.
This concept is really important because
if you think about it from a product
person or an engineering person's head,
they create moral hazards for each
other. So, let me explain. Let's say
you're the head of product and I'm the
head of engineering. And I tell you,
"Hey, we should stop building all
features because we need to break up our
monolith into a microservices platform
and it will take five years." As the
head of product, you're going to be
pretty upset about that, right? Because
this is impacting your ability to evolve
the business so on and so forth, right?
If the organization lets me have its
way, then what are you going to do for
the next five years? The flip side
happens. So, from an engineering
perspective, I think that we deal with
this all the time where the product
person says, "He said it's going to take
like two months." And the product person
says, "Ship it in three weeks. You know,
cut a bunch of corners. Just do it."
Well, guess what? Who gets the sev calls
in the middle of the night when things
are not going right? customers are
complaining. Not the product manager,
the engineers do. And so, these types of
trade-offs are often times best managed
if there is one person managing them.
And if you have to reconcile that at the
CEO level who also has to run, you know,
sales, marketing, operations so on and
so forth, they're just going to be too
split-headed. Those are great examples
when you might want to put it in one
person. The downside is that the person
you hire becomes very critical. They
might be more of an engineer or more of
a product person. And so, they will have
biases. And then the second thing is
that they may be weak in the domain. I,
for example, have held product and
technology roles simultaneously. But
generally speaking, I do not take on
those roles if I don't have expertise on
the product side. So, as an example,
I've been approached for work in
healthcare. I don't know anything about
healthcare. And I'm too scared as the
head of product to make a bad decision
about a healthcare product decision. So,
I think in those cases, you really need
a domain expert. So, those are some
examples where there may be reasons why
you can't even do it. And there are
reasons why you might want to combine
them. The final thing is that combined
roles, hiring that head typically is
very difficult. So, if you speak to
executive recruiting firms, it
represents somewhere between, you know,
two to five percent of their searches.
It has been increasing in the last two
to five years. And so, I think from an
industry perspective, what you'll find
is there's going to be more demand for
those individuals. So, those searches
are increasing, but they're still a
fairly low percentage, like probably
under 10% even in 2023. Uh the next one
I wanted to ask is to dive a little bit
more into this see the structuring. I've
been in like teams where you're actually
split by say components, entities, or
libraries, or even domains that you work
on. Is that a good way of doing
restructuring? The entity model I think
works for fairly stable situations.
Often times you do need that entity
model anyway because if everybody does
everything, then nobody owns anything.
So, that's very useful. The challenge
with the entity model comes when there's
a lot of entropy happening in the
system. And because what you'll also
find is, you know, some initiatives
might be cross-cutting across many
entities. So, for example, the user
entity. The user entity might be a
classic example of a limiting factor,
right? Everybody wants to get onto the
user entity's road map. And so, if the
user entity is affiliated with one
initiative or another, say like the
marketing team owns the user entity,
then they're going to block out
effectively every other person's request
to that entity. So, you know, how you
organize initiatives is really
important. If entities are completely
disassociated with initiatives or user
journeys, you'll often times have
problems because you'll find that those
user journeys are going to be either be
broken or you're going to work around
them. So, you know, for your listeners,
like a user journey might be the
acquisition flow. What happens when the
person goes from the visitor site, signs
up, and then does their first
transaction. If the visitor site and the
sign up is disconnected from the first
transaction, then every time you want to
acquire customers, right? Every time you
need to make a change to the teams
that's doing the first transaction, you
have to get on the road map and things
get slowed down. And so, potentially,
you might want to reorg all the entities
around a user journey where there might
be like a GM around it. But it can't be
done. I think that makes a lot of sense
because I think it would also be useful
for the user because if you follow a
user journey. There's another question I
wanted to ask also in terms of some
organizations, they also consider like
say dedicated frameworks, components,
and platforms when while they're
restructuring. What's your take on that?
I would consider them constraints in the
problem of reorganization. I've been at
companies that have this where you might
have like old Pearl code or old PHP
code. Unfortunately, those individuals
are so kind of landlocked because it's
very difficult to take a Pearl
programmer and put them on the front end
and do JavaScript, right? I think in the
long run, there's motivation for
administrators to standardize their
stack as much as possible because that
way you can move people around. The
second challenge that I think is a
tension within most technology companies
in terms of frameworks. How much of you
build yourself versus how much of an
ecosystem do you adopt that has a vast
number of libraries? It might be
intuitive for say engineers to just say,
"Well, I'm going to use like the most
heavily adopted ecosystem. Why would I
use Ember versus React, right? Which has
a ton of packages. One of the things
that you'll start to realize and that
there's an amazing blog post by Spolsky
in like the early 2000s where he talks
about the law of leaky abstractions.
Let's tell your readers about it.
I'll definitely add I don't think I can
summarize it, but I clearly remember
that and I remember being so struck by
that post. It was beautifully I don't
think I have it in the show notes there,
but yeah, that's something to add. The
law of leaky abstractions is amazing
because what it says is effectively the
things that we use libraries,
frameworks, and things like that to save
time. Eventually they become their own
maintenance headache because they may
have bugs that are outside of our
organization. I personally had this
issue where, you know, I have open
source projects and I rely on libraries,
they don't get maintained anymore. And
next thing I know, I'm forking the
source code and I'm coding, you know,
code that I don't even fully understand
just to be able to make my code work.
You know, these are the kinds of things
that, you know, are technology decisions
that may dramatically impact how you
deliver, you know, your product. In our
world, I think some of the more larger
tectonic changes I remember include
like, you know, Magento 1 and Magento 2.
Those are totally incompatible. Angular
Angular 1 and Angular 2 totally
incompatible. How many people got bit by
that transition where they had a full-on
Angular app and then they had to rewrite
their entire front end just for Angular
2. That's painful. How you choose your
frameworks can dramatically impact not
only who you hire, but also what work
you need to do. It's very interesting,
very insightful. Since you talked about
frameworks, I also have to ask you, does
it also make sense to have a dedicated
architecture team or an enterprise
architecture team in the scenario then?
I personally, me versus, you know, best
practice, I prefer to have the senior
leaders to be very technical, that the
people managers at least at the
architecture level because I think it's
very hard for people managers who manage
engineers who are not technical because
that means that they don't understand
how the game is played. I view them as
coaches. This is like having, you know,
imagine a sports team where the coach
has never played the game, right? Or
doesn't understand the nuances of games.
I think that's not a good precedent.
Now, with that being said, I think the
more senior engineers, they can be
expensive. And so, in order to get
economies of scale, sometimes it's
useful to have a group of very senior
engineers in an architecture group that
can, you know, provide guidance.
However, how you run that group can be
done in many different ways and some of
them are very bad. The architecture
group, for example, is oftentimes the
limiting factor because teams are forced
to essentially go through an
architecture review, the calendar is
backed up, and all of a sudden
software's not shipped, you know, that's
not good, right? As a leader and as
somebody looking at the structure of the
organization, you have to make sure that
the architecture group itself does not
become a limiting factor. You've got me
thinking there. Yeah, that's really good
there. Good one over there. I guess I
was going to ask you a question on
whether engineering managers should be
able to write code and I think you've
kind of said that they should be
technical. So, would your answer there
be say yes? I think so. Also, I wonder
why they wouldn't be able to write code.
I mean, maybe I'm just old school, but I
mean, writing software is so fun. I
think real technologists, first of all,
I will say most engineering managers, if
they're really good at engineering
management, they do not have time to
write code at work. I don't know why
engineers wouldn't write code even if
they don't have the ability to do it
full-time. And And most engineering
managers shouldn't have that time
because they would otherwise be doing it
a disservice to their org. But writing
code is so fun. I think if you stop
writing code, you stop being able to
empathize with your team at a deep
level. And I think that becomes
problematic. When your team says, "Hey,
you know, my work life is not as fun
because of this or that," you won't
understand why they're complaining. You
know, one of the biggest reasons why
engineers complain about burnout isn't
because they're overworked, it's because
they're doing work that they don't want
to do. Most software engineers have had
this experience where they're in this
flow, right? They're writing code and
it's
working and they're coding. Nobody gets
burned out when they're having fun. You
have to have the ability to empathize
with your team at that level at a very
deep level. I'll ask you now the other
roles which we usually see, which is to
do with what's the difference between
say project manager, a scrum master, a
program manager, or sometimes you also
call you have a product operations
specialist. I think prior to the early
like 2000s, most projects were actually
run by engineering managers. So, that
effectively the scrum master or what we
call scrum masters these days is the
engineering manager. They would figure
out who does what and then say this is
when things are due. I think that has
shifted dramatically. I think there one
of the big reasons is because the
industry doesn't have real tools to
bring up engineering managers and so
engineering managers oftentimes are
particularly good at driving
deliverables. And so, the engineering
manager role has been marginalized and
this has now propped up multiple
different roles. Generally speaking, I
think a lot of the things that you
talked like the different titles are
somewhat synonymous, which is either
getting the team to do something or
coordinating efforts between different
teams. They can be important. I think it
you'll find that the most efficient
organizations actually still run in a
way where the engineering managers are
the ones that are responsible for
delivery. I found that organizations
that have a lot of non-engineering folks
responsible for delivery, they can be
rather bloated. Okay, so I'll step back
one level higher because I want to ask
you a question also about what are the
different ways in which a company can
structure say the security teams like
between corporate IT and the platforms.
And sometimes I also see that in many
organizations the IT or the CISO, they
report to the office of the CFO. So,
could you explain IT versus AppSec.
Let's start with that one. The problem
with AppSec reporting into traditional
security is that AppSec engineers are
much closer to software engineering. And
so, in order to get the best result, a
lot of folks decide to embed application
security within infrastructure teams. I
think that's a very common modality, but
it can be a fight because if an HR
perspective, it's weird. You're like,
"Why is there a security person here
when all the security people should be
here?" And so, that's where you see that
tension. But I think you'll find that
most heads of engineering would prefer
to have AppSec in-house and then
hopefully also make sure that AppSec is
not one person's job. So, hopefully
AppSec is advocacy and that AppSec is
everybody's job and so that we build
security into the code up front versus
trying to QA it out on the back end.
That's just not going to work. With
regards to why IT sometimes moves into
the office of the CFO, as the company
matures, especially say in the US where
compliance becomes very important, IT
becomes more of a compliance exercise
and an audit exercise. And so, you'll
find that the the typical IT checklist,
like how do you off-board the employees,
how do you on-board the employees, like,
you know, so on and so forth. You know,
that sort of like checklist activity
feels more like accounting and so they
end up effectively in the accounting
realm. As a person who has managed IT
before, I will also tell you that IT
struggles getting managed by a head of
engineering. The head of engineering is
typically interested in building things,
running a business. They're not really
interested like figuring out like
whether or not what the new MacBook
replacement policy is for the company or
like whether or not we should, you know,
renew our G Suite license. It's such a
big task switch even though it's all
related to computers. But there's a
third thing though that is in the middle
and this is where things get
complicated, which is oftentimes you
have internal applications. And whether
or not internal applications should be,
you know, part of engineering or the
office of the CFO, this is where things
get very messy. What happens to the data
warehouse? The finance folks oftentimes
need the data warehouse to reconcile
their books. You do not know how much
the company has made without deep
integration into the data pipeline into
production. You know, Salesforce
integration is a constant problem for
many people. Does Salesforce and
Salesforce integration live in
engineering or in the office of the CFO?
My personal sort of lived experience is
that for better or worse, some of these
domains can get rather complicated and
so they're better off being held back
into the office of the CTO along with
all the data pipeline work and keeping
the data warehouse up. Since you talked
about data, I mean, this is a little bit
different. I I wanted to ask you about
the relationship between analytics and
data science. Again, that you see that
there is some companies actually choose
to combine both of these teams, the
analytics and the data science, and some
keep it separate. So, why is that? Why
does that happen? I think the root of
the issue happens in terms of how the
analytics team is used. There are many
forms of analytics, right? There's
product analytics and then there's like
say, I would call them like more, you
know, corporate analytics. And corporate
analytics might have things like
forecasting as part of their workload.
They're pretty different workloads. But
product analytics becomes really
problematic because the reality is is
data scientists actually do a ton of
product analytics themselves. If you
look at their typical data science
pipeline, you know, the first part is
sorting the data, right? And then they
have to clean the data and then they
have to augment the data and then they
have to look at the data, right? A large
part of their work is deeply
understanding the data and that can be
augmented by, you know, folks that are
actually in the analytics space. That
frees up your data scientists to
actually, you know, think about, you
know, building the models themselves. I
would consider to be related but quite
different. So, they're very
complementary. The challenge is that if
you just strictly look at analytics,
there's a bunch of iron that the
analytics teams use regardless of your
product analytics or corporate
analytics. like you might need like a
star schema or you might all own a data
warehouse. And so, now things get tricky
again between say engineering and some
other function because who owns, you
know, keeping that database up or that
data lake up. So, it really, really
depends. Most of the time, I would say
these decisions are largely dependent on
who the heads of the organizations are
and whether or not they know the domain
or not.
The last question I want to ask in this
section is is there an optimal team size
for software engineering teams that is
good for productivity and efficiency? I
think everybody has an opinion about
this. So, I'm going to state the
opinions of famous people. Andy Grove,
he's the former Intel CEO founder. I
don't know if he's a founder, but he was
definitely Intel for many years. His
number is seven. He says that the
optimal number of people to manage for
any manager is eight, which means seven
direct reports plus the manager. Over
the years, I have found this to be
largely true. There are some individuals
that can do an amazing job of managing
more than seven. There's a maybe a
question as to why it might be true. My
personal theory, having like, you know,
read research papers on human
performance and short-term memory, it
turns out short-term memory for humans
is seven chunks. This is also why in
some countries like the US, phone
numbers are seven. You know, it's like
an area code plus seven digits. Back in
the old days, people used to memorize
phone numbers.
These days it's irrelevant, but you
know, you could have a huge number, but
you know, for old people, they remember
that they used to have to memorize the
phone numbers. So, that's why the phone
numbers are seven and I think you'll
find that managers are going to be more
effective at seven. I think when you
have lower, let's say you have a manager
of four people. And let's say they all
they do is management. The obvious and
uncomfortable question is what do those
people do all day? And especially if
they manage managers, then there's a
real question as to you know, what value
does that manager add? And so, you know,
what when you look at reorgs, often
times the middle managers are impacted
because the flow of information, those
middle managers end up being a
pass-through. What managers, they have a
very uncomfortable job. I like to say
that managers' main jobs are two things.
One is to say no or two is to say yes,
but or yes, and. The whole reason that
person exists is to reframe the work. If
you just pass the work through, then
you're not needed. Then the person at
the top will just tell your people to do
the work. You don't need to be there.
You know, there are those managers that
don't manage a whole lot of people, you
know, end up being at risk to get cut.
Okay, that's a good tip to know, I think
for the listeners. Yeah, we're coming
towards the final part of the show and I
have to ask you a few questions like now
that we've gone through a lot of the
reasons why reorgs would happen and also
about software. I wanted to ask you how
do you measure the success of a reorg?
Do you have any examples that you can
share of an organization that had
considerable market success after reorg?
I think we had quite a bit of success at
Upwork after our reorg. So, we did a big
reorg once right before we went public.
Very similar to what we described you
and I just talked about where we
identified certain key user journeys and
we affiliated those domain teams with
those user journeys. So, effectively the
user journeys had a GM. So, for example,
the acquisition teams, they would be
very focused on the user onboarding
journey and they had metrics that they
were trying to drive towards. But they
also had all the domains that would
allow them to generally make the changes
they want without talking to, say,
another GM. And I think that was very,
very effective in the sense that it
allowed, you know, teams, essentially a
scrum of scrums, to be able to operate
fairly independently without getting on
each other's roadmaps and they
effectively had a collection of teams.
And so, with each month, rather than
going through, you know, large roadmap
reviews, you would just, you know, talk
to each individual team and say, "Hey,
what were the things that you tried to
do, you know, this quarter or this
month?" We did monthly ops reviews. And,
you know, how did your metrics change
from month to month? And that was very,
very effective. Some of the initiatives,
one of them ended up propelling the
company to an IPO in 18 months. The
other metric that I would say is just,
you know, employee happiness. I think
you'll actually know if it works fairly
quickly because employees will tell you
when they don't work and the employees
will tell you that it's working. And so,
if you can pull off a change and people
are like very excited or they're like,
"This makes so much sense." Or they're
very motivated, then you know you've
done a good job. Um, but it's very hard
to pull that off when you've let people
go. I think anytime you impact people,
it's very difficult to call success just
because of the nature of what happened.
How do you recognize failure? Is that
just through employee feedback or again
with the operational efficiencies? Yeah,
this I think different people will
answer this differently, so I can only
answer to my way. What personally
bothers me when I see leaders operate,
you know, reorgs, they let people go and
then they hire the same people back very
soon. That happens. To me, that shows
that the job was not done well. I don't
know if the employees will ever
recognize that. Of course, everybody's
happy that, "Oh, they came back to the
company. Wonderful." To me, it shows a
lack of foresight and thought that there
was not clear thinking at the management
level that you had to do that. I've also
seen companies that, you know, cut too
deep and then they, you know, try to
improve morale through, you know, team
events and things like that. That to me,
like from an employee perspective, might
seem like, "Okay, things are better."
But from my metric of leadership, it
means that you did not do the job. I
think if you're going to do something
hard, you try your darndest A, not to do
it and then B, not to undo it. If you
undo it, it's not successful. You did
not do a good job. Okay, so I guess the
last question I want to ask you is based
on all of this that you've said. Is
there any personal experience or maybe
an example where you learned a valuable
lesson from a mistake that you made
during a reorg? The biggest mistakes
I've made have always been due to
communication. I have a preference, as I
mentioned, to signal reorgs early. So, I
do not like to surprise teams. But the
problem is that that puts an enormous
amount of pressure to execute that
reorg. And there have been times when I
was not able to get the management team
to align fast enough on the reorg. And
so, it just kept dragging. That is very,
very devastating because it impacts the
roadmap, it impacts morale. Also, people
start leaving. Sometimes the people you
want to keep start leaving, which is
bad. I think being very careful about
moving as fast as possible is key. But
there are so many unknowns. You just
don't know like who's going to disagree
with you, who has a different opinion,
whose input you need to get, whose
buy-off you need to get. Those things
are very, very difficult to predict. I
wonder if there's kind of testing that
you can do before the actual reorg, like
a scenario like a DR scenario test that
we usually do. I wonder if that's
something that happens into a reorg. In
this case where I made a mistake before
I signaled it, I had drafted a 25-page
memo on the whys, various solutions in
broad strokes. I thought I had
alignment. When you start putting names
to boxes,
I couldn't get it together. It's really
hard because I forgot who said this, but
I think engineers do this, too. We plan
a lot, right? We do a lot of planning
and the reason is that we want to
anticipate problems ahead of time. The
challenge is that the biggest problems
that we face are usually the unexpected.
So, no amount of documentation I had was
going to help in this case because the
things that I got burned by was outside
of the 25-page document. So, I don't
know what to do. And that's all the
questions I have and it's been quite
insightful. Thank you for coming on the
show, Han. I guess before I let you go,
I guess the question I need to ask is
where can people reach you in cyberspace
if they wanted to? You can reach me on
LinkedIn. You can find me as Han Yuan or
Han Shen Yuan. Let's spell H A N Y U A N
and you should be able to find me. I
have like funny hair, so that'll
hopefully identify me from everybody
else. Thank you once again and this is
Priyanka Raghavan for Software
Engineering Radio. Thanks for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.